Partial Inventory of the Wilbur J. Peterkin Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Wilbur J. Peterkin papers
1943-1994
76018
Hoover Institution Archives
11 manuscript boxes, 2 envelopes, 1 album box, 3 motion picture film reels, 1 microfilm reel, 2 videotape cassettes, memorabilia (4.5 linear feet)
Diary transcripts, letters, reports, maps, photographs, motion picture film, and memorabilia, relating to Chinese communist forces and the Japanese occupation of China during World War II. Includes weapons, clothing and equipment used by Chinese communists during World War II.
Peterkin, Wilbur J., 1904-
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1976.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Scope and Content of Collection
Diary transcripts, letters, reports, maps, photographs, motion picture film, and memorabilia, relating to Chinese communist forces and the Japanese occupation of China during World War II. Includes weapons, clothing and equipment used by Chinese communists during World War II.
Biographical Note
Wilbur Peterkin was a Colonel in the United States Army. He served as the Executive Officer and Commanding Officer of the United States Army Observer Group, more commonly referred to as the Dixie Mission, with Chinese communist forces in Yenan, China, 1944-1945.
United States. Army.; United States. Observer Mission to Yenan, 1944-1945.; Communism--China.; Guerrillas--China.; Motion pictures.; Sino-Japanese Conflict, 1937-1945.; Video tapes.; World War, 1939-1945--China.
- Not yet described (Box 1-4)
- Photographs, 1943-1945 (Box 5)
  - September 1943 - December 1943 (Box-folder 5: 1)
  - January 1944 - February 1944 (Box-folder 5: 2)
  - March 1944 - May 1944 (Box-folder 5: 3)
  - June 1944 - July 1944 (Box-folder 5: 4)
  - August 1944 (Box-folder 5: 5)
  - September 1944 (Box-folder 5: 6)
  - October 1944 (Box-folder 5: 7)
  - November 1944 (Box-folder 5: 8)
  - December 1944 (Box-folder 5: 9)
  - January 1945 - February 1945 (Box-folder 5: 10)
  - March 1945 - June 1945 (Box-folder 5: 11)
  - July 1945 - September 1945 (Box-folder 5: 12)
  - Post-1945 (Box-folder 5: 13)
  - Undated, likely 1943-1945 (Box-folder 5: 14-15)
- Maps and Outline of Voyage, circa 1945 (Box-folder 5: 16)
- Small photo album, 1943-1945 (Box-folder 5: 17)
- Time"Specially printed for members of the U.S. armed forces overseas", December 10, 1945 (Box-folder 5: 18)
- Larger photographs, July 1944 - December 1944; pictures of maps, circa 1944 (Box-folder 5: 19)
- Peterkin: "Inside China: An Eyewitness Account of America's Mission in Yenan," preliminary draft, 1992 (Box-folder 5: 20)
- Photo negatives, circa 1944, 1978 (Box-folder 5: 21)
- Color photo slides, 1943 - 1945 (Box-folder 5: 22)
- 92 photographs depicting W. J. Peterkin's activities as executive and commanding officer of the U.S. Observer Mission to the Chinese Communists, 1944-1945 (Envelope A)
  Scope and Contents note
  Includes prints of Communist Chinese leaders and views of Yenan.
- Photo album of 245 prints of China, Nigeria, and India at the time of World War II, undated (Album fB)
- 66 prints depicting the International Peace Hospital with the Chinese communist forces, 1944 (Envelope C)
- Color Photo Slides, undated (Box-folder 8: 1)
- Photos of Yenan, 1944-1945 (Box-folder 8: 2)
- Photos, undated (Box-folder 8: 3)
- Photos and Negatives of Kweilin, 1944 (Box-folder 8: 4)
- Photos and Negatives, undated (Box-folder 8: 5)
- Photo Booklet, undated (Box-folder 8: 6)
- Correspondence, 1943-1945 (Box 6)
  - July 1943-August 1943 (Box-folder 6: 1)
  - September 1943 (Box-folder 6: 2)
  - October 1943-December 1943 (Box-folder 6: 3)
  - January 1944-February 1944 (Box-folder 6: 4)
  - March 1944 (Box-folder 6: 5)
  - April 1944 (Box-folder 6: 6)
  - May 1944 (Box-folder 6: 7)
  - June 1944 (Box-folder 9: 1)
  - July 1944 (Box-folder 9: 2)
  - August 1944-September 1944 (Box-folder 9: 3)
  - January 1945-February 1945, April 1945 (Box-folder 9: 4)
  - May 1945-July 1945 (Box-folder 9: 5)
  - From Peterkin, Wilbur, to Peterkin, Dorothy
    - October-November 1943 (Box-folder 7: 1)
    - November 1943 (Box-folder 7: 2-3)
    - December 1943 (Box-folder 7: 4-5)
    - January 1944 (Box-folder 7: 6-7)
    - February-March 1944 (Box-folder 10: 1)
    - July 1944 (Box-folder 10: 2)
    - August 1944 (Box-folder 10: 3)
    - September 1944 (Box-folder 10: 4)
    - October 1944 (Box-folder 10: 5)
    - November-December 1944 (Box-folder 10: 6)
    - January-February 1945 (Box-folder 10: 7)
    - March 1945 (Box-folder 10: 8)
    - June 1945 (Box-folder 10: 10)
    - July 1945 (Box-folder 10: 11)
    - August 1945 (Box-folder 11: 1)
    - September 1945 (Box-folder 11: 2)
  - General Correspondence to Peterkin, Dorothy, 1945 (Box-folder 11: 3)
  - From Schick, Frances to Peterkin, Dorothy, 1945 (Box-folder 11: 4)
  - From Peterkin, Wilbur to Peterkin, Anne, 1944 (Box-folder 11: 5)
  - To Peterkin, Dorothy, July 1945 (Box-folder 7: 2)
- Motion picture films, 1944 (Film shelf Film shelf)
  - China U.S.A.O.S., 1944-1945
    Film shot by Wilbur J. Peterkin while stationed in China during World War II. 16mm, color and black and white, silent. Roll 2. Detailed contents list below. Use copy reference number: 76018_f_0008113
    - October 5, 1944
      - Occasion of Legion Merit for Colonel Barrett
      - Chu Teh, Mao Tse Tung, Ludden, Barrett, and members of Mission
      - General Bergin- who presented Legion of Merit
      - Gunther Stein - Brooks Atkinson in door of plane
      - Yeh Chien Ying, Madam Chu Teh
    - February 5, 1945
      - Colonel Morris DePass
    - February 11, 1945
      - Chinese New Year and band with gifts for mission
    - April 18-20, 1945
      - Trip to Yenchang oil fields; Peterkin, Lt. Col Dexheimer and Colonel Andrus and Mr. Yellachich
      - Oil wells pumped by man-power
      - Road cave in. 25 fords in about 69 miles.
    - May 1945
      - Lt. Happe (knit cap) and Sgt. White going to Varoff Field
      - Chinese weather observers and radio operators to be flown behind Japanese lines. Tai Hang.
      - Yenan Water system
    - June 1945
      - Orderlies planting vegetables after drough
      - Hsiao Ping photographer
      - Mr. Wu head of photography
    - March 23, 1945
      - Chungking
      - Threshing rice
    - March 25, 1945
      - Convoy Chunking-Yenan, 4 3/4 tons with 1 ton trailers and one jeep with trailer. Personnel Peterkin, Captain Pomeranze, MC, Catain William Glei, Captain Eaton, Lt. Proccino, Lt. Hauck, Sergeant Sevia Thorne OSS, Sgt. Richards, Corporal Peel, Lt. Happe
      - Lt. Hauck and Lt. Proccanino
      - Captain Pomeranze with dark glasses
      - Sgt. Thorne with dark glasses
      - Lt. Happe eating apple
      - Captain Glei no shirt eating apple
    - April 2, 1945
      - City of Paochi - camped on airfield
      - Kuo Min Tang soldier
      - Peterkin and camel - Yenan
    - June 27, 1945
      - B25 Lt. Happe and Sgt. White return from Varoff Field
    - July 4, 1945
      - Signal flare caught on telephone wire across river
      - Civilian William Taylor captured on Wake Island escaped from Japanese in North China and rescued by guerrillas
    - July 5, 1945
      - Political meeting with KMT, KCT, and other political parties
      - Yeh Chien Ying, Chun Yi, Mao Tse Tung, Madam Chou En Lai, etc.
      - Peterkin and laborers at Yenan airfield
      - Lt. Klein with young art student from Yu Lin Art Academy
    - September 3, 1945
      - Victory parade in Chungking
      - Victory Arch Chungking
    - September 13, 1945
      - Approach to Hause # 15, Peterkin's billet.
      - View from window of House #15
  - Mission to Yenan, Roll 5, circa 1944-1945
    Film shot by Wilbur J. Peterkin while stationed in China during World War II. 16 mm, black and white, silent. Roll 5. Use copy reference number: 76018_f_0008114
  - Dixie Compound, Roll 4, circa 1944-1945 (Film shelf Film shelf)
    Film shot by Wilbur J. Peterkin while stationed in China during World War II. 16mm, color, silent. Roll 4. Use copy reference number: 76018_f_0008799.
- Microfilm reel (Microfilm cabinet)
  - U.S. Military Observers in Yenan, China collected reports microfilm reel, 1944-1971 (bulk 1944-1946) (Microfilm 1)
    Includes four volumes of collected administrative and other reports concerning the Yenan Observer Group (Code Name: Dixie Mission; File No. Geog V China 334--Dixie Mission). The Yenan Observer Group arrived in Yenan, China, on July 22, 1944. The volumes were regraded unclassified by the Secretary of the Army in 1971.
    Volume 1 index: Army Ground Forces Resources Technical Staff; Air Ground Aid Service Section, American--Communist Relations, Colonel Dave Barrett's Reports, Miscellaneous Correspondence, Maps, Charts, Foreign Economics Administration, Ambassador Patrick J. Hurley
    Volume 2 index: Illustrations, Maps of areas, Interviews with Lt. George I. Nakamura, Nationalist--Communist Relations, Naval Intelligence, Operations Conditions, Order of Battle Section, Office of Strategic Services (OSS), Office of War Information (OWI), Personalities Involved, Propaganda
    Volume 3 index: Preliminary Story, Tenth Weather Squadron Detachment, Twentieth Bomber Command, Wind-Up Of Mission, Colonel Yeaton, Yensig Section (Proposed), china Theater Political History (by Fenton Keyes), G-5 Clandestine Branch History Excerpts
    Volume 4 is not indexed.